Active Directory Security Audit

A PowerShell-based security auditing tool for Windows systems — identifies vulnerabilities in user accounts, password policies, firewall configurations, open ports, and login activity.

About the Project

The tool automates common Windows security checks that administrators typically perform manually — making the process faster, repeatable, and less error-prone.

---

# Features

| Module | What it checks |

|  User Account Audit    | Lists all local accounts; flags active/default accounts |
|  Admin Privilege Check    | Lists members of the Administrators group |
|  Password Policy Analysis    | Checks min length, lockout threshold, expiry |
|  Active Session Monitoring      | Shows currently logged-in users |
|  Firewall Status                   | Checks Domain, Private, Public profile states |
|  Shared Folder Detection      | Lists all network shares on the system |
|  Open Port Scanning         | Shows all LISTENING ports (first 15) |
|  Failed Login Detection  | Reads Security Event Log for Event ID 4625 |
|  System Info           | Hostname and current user context |

---

# Technologies Used

- Language: PowerShell 5.1+
- Platform: Windows 10 / Windows Server 2019
- APIs: Windows Event Log, Windows Registry, NetSecurity
- Run As: Administrator (elevated privileges required)

---

# Files

```
Active_Directory_SecurityAudit/
│
├── AD_Audit.ps1       # Main audit script — read-only, safe to run
└── AD_Fix.ps1         # Remediation script — applies security fixes


---

# How to Run

Step 1 — Open PowerShell as Administrator

Step 2 — Navigate to the project folder

Step 3 — Run the audit

Step 4 — (Optional) Apply security fixes


 ⚠Run only on systems you own or have explicit authorization to audit. Unauthorized use is illegal.

---

# Sample Audit Checks

List all local users
net user

List administrator group members
net localgroup administrators

Check password and lockout policy
net accounts

Show all listening ports
netstat -an | findstr LISTENING

Check firewall status
netsh advfirewall show allprofiles state

Detect failed login attempts (Event ID 4625)
Get-WinEvent -FilterHashtable @{LogName='Security'; Id=4625} -MaxEvents 5

---

# What AD_Fix.ps1 Does

net accounts /minpwlen:8                   # Set minimum password length to 8
net accounts /lockoutthreshold:5           # Lock account after 5 failed attempts
net localgroup administrators Hp /delete   # Remove unnecessary admin
netsh advfirewall firewall set rule group="remote desktop" new enable=No    # Disable RDP

---

# References

1. Microsoft Corporation — [Windows PowerShell Documentation](https://learn.microsoft.com/powershell/)
2. Microsoft Corporation — [Active Directory Domain Services Overview](https://learn.microsoft.com/windows-server/identity/ad-ds/)
3. W. Stallings — *Cryptography and Network Security*, 8th ed., Pearson, 2023
4. Microsoft Corporation — [Windows Security Auditing](https://learn.microsoft.com/windows/security/)

---

# Disclaimer

This tool is intended **only for authorized security auditing** on systems you own or have written permission to test. The authors are not responsible for any misuse of this tool.
